Thank you MD. Monirul Islam Masuk.
Assalamu Alaikum, Good afternoon. Let's get started.

As we already know the Background and Significance of CMSME.
Let's see the types of industries and sectors of CMSME:
As per Industrial policy 2016, industries fall under this category are divided into Cottage industry,
Micro industry, Small industry and medium industry. These industries are further divided
into 3 sectors according to their business types: Manufacturing sector, service sector and trading business

Well, now the question is how should we identify which one is cottage,
Micro or which one is small or medium industry? And what will be the limit of loan to distribute
in each of these industries/sectors? According to the industrial policy 2016, and BB SmeSpd circular a cottage
industry may have fixed assets less than 10 Lac and may have employees maximum 15. We can distribute maximum
15 Lac loan limit if the cottage industry is in manufacturing sector.Similarly a micro industry in
manufacturing sector may have fixed assets between 10 to 75 Lac and employees between 16 to 30, and we may
distribute maximum 1 crore loan limit to this industry. A micro industry either in service or trading sector
may have fixed assets less than 10 Lac and employees maximum 15, and the loan limit is maximum 25 Lac for
service and 50 Lac for trading business. A small manufacturing industry may have fixed assets between 75 Lac
to 15 crore and employees between 31 to 120, the loan limit in this case is 20 crore. Again a small industry
in service or trading sector may have fixed assets between 10 Lac to 2 crore and employees between 16-50 or
6-10 sequentially. The loan limit for the both of these sectors is 5 crore. A medium manufacturing industry
may have fixed assets between 15 to 50 crore and employees between 121 to 300. For the garments sector it
can be up to 1000. The loan limit for this sector is 75 crore. For the medium service sector industry fixed
asset should have be in between 2 to 30 crore and employees between 51-120. The maximum loan limit for
this sector is 50 crore.

এবার দেখা যাক CMSME এর উচ্চ ও অগ্রাধিকার প্রাপ্ত ক্লাস্টার সমূহ কি কি রয়েছে। বাংলাদেশ ব্যাংকের SMESPD circular নং ৪/২২ অনুযায়ী ৬ টি উচ্চ অগ্রাধিকার প্রাপ্ত 
ও ১৩ টি অগ্রাধিকার প্রাপ্ত ক্লাস্টারের তালিকা দেওয়া হয়েছে। উচ্চ অগ্রাধিকার প্রাপ্ত ক্লাস্টারের তালিকায় রয়েছে .... অনুরূপভাবে অগ্রাধিকারপ্রাপ্ত ক্লাস্টারের তালিকায় রয়েছে ....

CMSME খাতের উন্নয়নের লক্ষ্যে বাংলাদেশ ব্যাংক বেশ কিছু সুবিধা  / স্কিম প্রণয়ন করে। এমনই একটি স্কিম হচ্ছে পুনঃ অর্থায়ন / Refinance স্কিম । এর সাথে সংশ্লিষ্টর
BB circular হচ্ছেঃ SMESPD circular 4/22. প্রাথমিকভাবে এই স্কিমের আওতায় গৃহীত ঋণের মেয়াদ হবে ৩ বছর, তবে ব্যবসার ধরণভেদে ও গ্রেস পিরিয়ড সহ
ঋণের মেয়াদ ৫ বছরের অধিক হবে না। এ স্কিমের আওতায় বিতরণকৃত মোট ঋণ/বিনিয়োগের ন্যূনতম ৬৫ (পয়ষট্টি) শতাংশ  উৎপাদন ও সেবা খাতে এবং সর্বোচ্চ ৩৫ (পঁয়ত্রিশ) 
শতাংশ ব্যবসা খাতে প্রদান করা যাবে।  অর্থায়নকারী ব্যাংক এ স্কিমের আওতায় বার্ষিক ২% (দুই শতাংশ) সুদে টাকা নিতে পারবে, আর গ্রাহকের ঋণের সুদ হার 
হবে ৭% (সাত শতাংশ)। ঋণসীমা নির্ধারণ হয় ২৫,০০০/- (পঁচিশ হাজার) টাকা হতে সর্বোচ্চ ৫,০০,০০,০০০/-(পাঁচ কোটি) টাকা। 

Well, thank you for your patience. Now I would like to invite my next team member Miss Kohinur Khatun
discuss further on CMSME financing. Assalamu Alaikum.